hello everyone thanks for joining the
seconds
meeting
where we're going to be discussing
chapter one
it's the active textbook group and it's
may 12 2022.
you can click on my screen and that will
show you the full screen
we updated the live meeting page a bit
and it's
just like all these other pages a work
in progress but hopefully this will be a
structure where
we'll be able to hear everyone's
perspective and leave the coda in a
better place than we found it
so what we'll do in the live meetings
which from here on out
or at least for here for the next two
and a half months or so are going to be
like
driven by the material
in the chapters and in the appendices
we're going to go to the questions page
and we're gonna look at the questions
that have been asked for that week for
that theme
and we're just gonna start with the most
upvoted questions and then we're gonna
be taking notes
in the answers in the discourse and
we'll go into a little bit more detail
when we flip to that page
and then after addressing questions for
probably most of the time and discussing
that
we'll go
pull back a little bit more broadly like
ideas
for that
week um
and then in the last minutes we can just
see if there's been any changes to the
project ideas
and start to see what people are excited
about applying active inference to
and then we'll end at the top of the
hour
and take a quick break and then there'll
be a tools organizational unit meeting
following for those who want to just
like listen or participate in dot tools
so let's head over to questions and i'm
going to hide the sidebar because we're
going to be mostly here in questions
okay
so it's awesome
and also control and plus minus or
control and scroll is like a good way to
resize how it looks
um
so this is our first week with this
format
and anyone's welcome to like
suggest a a variant or a different way
to carry this out but
um the co-organizers of the textbook
group kind of
thought we could
do something along these lines
the questions we're gonna be looking at
are in chapter one
so that's the chapter we're discussing
today
and we're going to start with the ones
that have the most upvotes in the
interesting
um
and just
spend a couple minutes on each of the
questions
and at any point
there are the affordances of just
listening
and also of course re-watching this
recording
there's also the affordance in gather to
raise your hand if you'd like to share
on that question that we're going to
have up
and additionally
in the um by clicking on the answers in
discourse
that will pull up like a focused view on
that question
and everybody can collaboratively edit
the answers in discourse and so it's
better to like add and be noisy even if
it's a bullet point list or an
incomplete sentence or there's
incoherence or it's contradictory those
are all fine
it just like adds information and
perspectives
to the question so yeah we're going to
go to each question
open up
the answers in discourse
read the question
see what has already been contributed in
the answers in discourse and then also
like if people want to share
other thoughts that they're having
that's awesome
and then also if anybody wants to be
like taking other notes just things that
are coming to mind that they don't want
to share
in a speaking way
or just taking some notes on what other
people are saying
um
so
let's just
go into it and i'll be just keeping an
eye for the raised hand in gather
or anybody who wants to speak so
um starting with this
first question
maybe we can have like a like addressed
during recording or something like that
but
so
how do you understand the distinction
between the high road and the low road
to active inference
what do you think is interesting or
useful about this distinction
so does anybody want to like just
summarize how they
were thinking about the high in the low
road or we can look at what um others
have already written here
what is the difference between the high
road and the low road
are there other roads
are there high and low roads to other
theories
what is this metaphor with the roads
so let's check out yes um ali and then
mallory
well i believe it's just um another term
for top-down or bottom-up approach in a
kind of way
and um well the
high road i believe starts uh from
the actualized mind itself and tries to
derive
the underlying mechanisms or underlying
principles
but the bottom-up approach or the
uh
in other words low road
uh tries to
start from
the elements
tries to start from the
unorganized elements let's say and
derive the higher mechanisms or higher
order mechanisms
actualizing the mind itself
thank you awesome allery
um yeah i was just gonna
maybe recapitulate i guess what i wrote
in the comments and
i see now that i probably should have
written straighten the answers in
discourse section so sorry about that um
but um
i really appreciated this
schematic
because
um
i've read
papers that i think come at active
inference from both of these angles and
in trying to understand
i don't know the framework i think
um
it wasn't super clear to me how all of
these different terms that are like
really nicely outlined in this figure
um figure 1.2
um
are related to one another so just to
have it
i think
laid out like this it was really very
very helpful um
and i think um
still being kind of new to the concepts
and and such i liked the way they framed
it in terms of kind of
um the high road describing
um
the kind of what and why
and the low road being more about the
how
um
i thought that was really
very useful
so yeah i really i love this and i i
saved it and we'll probably reference it
quite often
yeah agreed it's it's really uh useful
and it touches on
aristotle's multiple y's
where some of the y's are are more like
hows
um or they're sort of proximate
mechanisms or more ultimate mechanisms
um and and we can like look at figure
1.2 so active inference is in the middle
and the high road i guess this is the
starting train stop here with a free
energy principle
um which
some later questions also might invoke
and then it kind of goes down to active
inference whereas starting with bayes
theorem
also gets us to
sentience
behavior
sentient being like sensing and feeling
and acting not
as much on the um
qualia and experiential side
um
so what else do we
have in the answers so high road what
and why
that is
starting with sort of the organismal
imperative or or like um ali i think
said there that the actualized mind and
then what are the underlying principles
that make
adaptive behavior adaptive behavioral
systems
working
down you know the castle in the sky is
the adaptive behavior and intelligent
cognitive behavior
what
is under it
and then the low road
doesn't begin with that imperative it
starts with like the elements
like the low road starting with base
none of these necessarily have to be or
at least maybe until you get to like
bayesian brain
these don't have to be adaptive
a generative model doesn't have to be
resisting entropy
so it's sort of like here's where we see
a lot of the elements in the machinery
and then on the top is more of the
self-organization
resistance to dissipation autopilosis
how are you going to get there you have
to be minimizing your surprise
what does that actually
entail and then active inference is like
this intermediate stop
and again maybe there's other roads or
there's other paths
um
yeah
so any other thoughts on high road and
low road or we'll continue to the next
question
this is just being
introduced in chapter one
because the following chapters two and
three which we're going to get to after
the appendix a and b
are going to detail the low road and the
high road
so this is kind of like a a map for some
of the next steps that we're going to be
engaging in
okay
next question
the concept
of organisms minimizing surprise is
introduced on page six
how are prior assumptions or beliefs
established when the organism is in new
or novel environments
so anyone can raise their hand or
take a note here
um
mallory or ali with raisins
one helpful approach might be to think
about like the questions asking about
new and novel environments so are we
dealing with
um categorical novelty
or with like quantitative novelty like i
was measuring the temperature and then
i'm in a new environment where the
temperature is different
that's one type of novelty but there
might also be like this like
novelty
at an even higher level with like i was
looking at
um
previously i was looking at temperature
and now i'm in a place where i'm having
priors about smell
so that's like a sort of intermodal
or like
a different
type of thing that's being tracked so
that's a categorical novelty
as opposed to
just updating the temperature parameter
in a different temperature room
whether
the person who asked it is here or not
um oh yes okay ali and mike go for it
uh yeah um well again if we're talking
about um
the um human mind
uh
i mean uh if
from the priors
we can infer that uh well it's something
that's
kind of innate in human minds is
something uh wired and
i mean
perhaps genetically or uh in any other
biologically
hardwired way but
well
again yes the definition of novel
situation varies uh
according to
what we're exactly referring to
and if uh a novel situation is something
that the organism uh hasn't
uh ever presented with uh well in that
case uh these prior
these priors or these innate tendencies
won't
help it very much so in that case
it should probably go
along the
way of
constructing
posteriors more actively i believe than
in any regular situation
thank you ali
uh jessica
and then mike and then steve
hi um i think
maybe like in this situation even though
the um
the agent might be encountering
something that has an experience before
they might use something as proxy that
they already know
and sort of like project
those understanding into
that new situation and then it's through
action etc then they're gonna be
updating like okay how true is it or
isn't
to what they understand but they might
be making some kind of projection based
on what they already know and things
that look similar to that new experience
awesome thank you uh mike and stephen
yeah i was just gonna comment um
in the case where the organism is brand
new and has no experience um
i think ali's comments cover this a bit
that it will have to be updating its
priors fairly rapidly and
presumably starting with sort of a wider
distribution
great stephen
yes along the lines of what jessica was
saying
there
has been some work in systematizing that
as case-based reasoning
not necessarily in a
bayesian framework here
but as a
derivative of expert systems
where
when you get a
new scenario you try to match that
against previous scenarios that you've
already seen and adapted
however necessary to
meet the new observations
so that might be a place to look for
uh inspiration
thanks
yeah and in in the
ontology work and in a lot of these
questions there's often like a narrow
answer and then a broader answer like
the narrow answer would be well again if
all your bayesian model is doing
is looking at the thermometer reading
and then doing a column and filter and
inferring the temperature in the room
well then the answer of what happens
when you put it under water or what
happens when you ask it to predict scent
it's kind of like a trivial answer which
is it's just not a parameter in that
script
nothing happens
and then that's like the narrower answer
which is
often very deflationary or like very
trivial
answers
and then there's also a broader question
like in the ecological context or in the
organismal context in the expert applied
context
what happens when there are these
different qualitative and quantitative
types of novelty
and so sometimes it's like
um
there we are in the middle again with
the deflationary or the narrow being too
obvious and too simple to be brought
into action
and then the bigger question like how do
experts
in medicine or
some other field how do they handle
different types of novelty is like
that's its own
research question and agenda
awesome
any other thoughts on this question
about
priors and it's also very important note
that surprise is always relative to
expectations
which are priors in the bayesian context
and those are granted by the generative
model so surprise is not just free
floating it's in relationship to the
outcomes as expected by an organism for
example jessica your hands raised
otherwise we'll go to the next question
awesome
okay this question i think is pretty
similar to the previous
um one so if anybody wants to give a
thought otherwise no worries
are the high road low road the only
roads to active inference or my active
be like rome
which i guess we can unpack a little bit
many slash all roads leading to it
um jf
yes that's more of a general question uh
uh
if for example if what you're trying to
understand is race cars right and you
develop a mathematical framework a given
number of measurements like the the
weight of the car the length of the car
the torque of the engine the adhesion of
the tires the friction and whatnot
you're able to predict how well the the
race car is going to perform in
different conditions and whatnot
does that mean that you're an expert in
race cars does that explain the race car
could you engineer a race car
based on this knowledge so
talking about multiple the different
roads um
one road through the free energy
principle i think is an analytical
uh road
that looks at
the outcomes
of the
the machinery of the uh the living
beings that try to maintain homeostasis
but how much does it say about the
implementation
of those
organisms
it says
many things but does it say everything
that we deem
might deem interesting
so what are the limitations of of this
this this uh
framework the the
the the active inference framework uh
defined by the free energy principle
what are its limitations
on top of what it the
given its capabilities which are which
are i think uh enormous but there are
limitations and and if there are
limitations that means there are there
must be other roads
that
can be taken
to
circumvent these limitations
thank you great comment ali
uh well
delusion gathering in a thousand
plateaus
has
laid out um the concept of rhizome i
don't know if you're familiar with the
concept of rhizome as opposed to
an arborescence structure
well
basically the concept of rhizome
uh expounds a
structure and now a knowledge structure
in which every concept can potentially
be connected to every other concept
without having to go through a principle
uh trunk
of a knowledge struct a knowledge tree
let's say but uh in an arborescent
structure and not arborescens knowledge
structure
everything branches off from a principal
trunk from a principle
uh let's say
uh
and i believe that in active imprints uh
a rhizomatic approach can also be
uh
explored
and
i mean
not only by
uh
approaching uh
to different concepts via the uh
high road or the low road
main or principal trunk
it can potentially be approached from
uh seemingly unrelated concepts too
awesome like to
maybe even approach a limitation or a
seemingly unrelated concept
both the high and the low road in this
textbook
are formal and they're both grounded in
like mathematical symbols
so are there qualitative
or
non-mathematical
roads
maybe
some of the early roads are mathematical
but
is it possible that a future
road or path or tunnel or
choose your travel metaphor might not be
that case
and then and then thanks for sharing
that um the resource there
because um this is another interesting
angle
which um
[Music]
various people have traced this
evolution of visual metaphor
where it's like things are ladder-like
and scalar
and then there's more of a bifurcating
tree
and then that becomes
um critiqued or complexified into more
of a network
like
with introgression among species for
example so there's sort of this movement
from
linear
through a tree like a directed acyclic
graph towards something that's more
networked
so
that's um a lot of interesting
ideas anything else that people want to
add or we'll continue on
okay
on page 10 they write creatures engaging
in active inference actively seek out
salient sensory observations that
resolve their uncertainty
so
what is the relationship between
salience in the kind of observation that
reduces uncertainty
why is the relationship between salience
observation and uncertainty this way
how does active inference frame this
relationship similarly or different from
which other specific frameworks
so someone wrote
i like this question a lot eager to get
a better understanding of what
constitutes salience
is salience referencing information that
is self-evidence or information that is
precise and surprising or dot dot dot
yes i think um
attention and salience
is addressed more in papers on active
inference
than at least just from a preliminary
pass of the book so attention and
metacognitive mechanisms are not going
to be
um
a core
feature
in the book however there's again been a
lot of interesting work on like the
neurobiology and the
computational aspects of salience and
attention
we can click on the word and and see
a definition but this is not like the
final definition this is just what
some have gotten to salience is the
extent to which a cue or an observation
commands the attention of an agent given
their regime of attention so potentially
a little bit taught logical
like a salient
observation is something that is
grabbing attention a salient cue is
something that commands attention steven
[Music]
yes i would say that especially if we're
defining it in
that way that there are
two elements to salience and one is what
was
pointed out in the question i guess that
you are reducing
uncertainty
but there is also the question of what
uncertainty is worth reducing
and that gets into
utility and where
where it makes sense to explore
i don't know if we want to
choose to change the definition of
salience to just be the second of those
or leave it as having both of those
elements
thanks
mallory
um i think something i don't necessarily
understand um which i would appreciate
maybe somebody speaking to a little bit
is um
this is related actually to a question i
put in earlier about the distinction
between
um
perception and learning but um
something that grabs attention
are we distinguishing so that would say
that something is
like the point that was just made
something is salient if it reduces
uncertainty
um if we're also
attending to things in order to actively
construct a niche that is consistent
with
um
our
model of the world
would
would we not consider that
something
like that object as attracting attention
as opposed to art like how do we
distinguish a guess between active
sampling and attending
um
and how is that related to salient so
something salient either if it
um
is
surprising
or
if it is
like um
serving the
purpose of kind of like fulfilling a
prediction i i'm not sure i understand
that kind of distinction i'm not sure
that makes sense but
awesome question
and
this is one reason why
looking at the formalisms and how
they're framed will help us because in
the purely
english linguistic realm
we could
imagine sentences
of any
type
so in the active inference formalisms
what what are being tagged with salience
which variables are said to reflect
salience and then are they
um or in what ways are they
related to this concept of surprise
which we're going to get to in a
question soon
versus
utility
and this is also speaking to
the way that expectations and
preferences
in active inference are framed
differently than in certain other
frameworks
um can i jump in and just ask another
question about this question rather than
an answer which is um
wouldn't some data be salient
if if it's even if it's sensible like we
might have two levels of salience
so i just put this quote in about the
notion of a umvelt being a more or less
broad series of elements called carries
of significance or marks which are the
only things that interest the animal now
interest the animal is one thing but
even just perceiving those marks as
existing i mean active inference does
have room for that in terms of each
agent having some sensory data so you
could say well since i can't see
uh infrared light
it's not salient to me
when i'm out in a field of flowers but a
bee
can see that
i think it's you can see all infrared or
ultraviolet i came over which one um
so you know it may be a salient concept
for me as a thinking agent but it's not
one that's sailing for me when i'm
navigating a field of flowers basically
nice thanks for bringing in um umvelt
and
a lot of ecological psychology terms
do make their way to active and so then
you brought up like levels of perception
and salience for example there's things
that are outside of the wavelength that
can be perceived so photons are not
going to be perceived at that wavelength
but then there might be within the
visible range
novel
arrangements
like there's something moving there
or there might be something that is
static yet commands attention like the
mona lisa
so what is happening when somebody's
regime of attention is fixated on a
static artifact
versus
something where they're being fixated on
something that's rapidly changing like a
movie
mallory in the chat you wrote can folks
recommend papers so definitely people
can recommend papers
anywhere they see fit
and one place to check out is in the
bottom of our coda in the live streams
under the live stream tab
you'll find like
45 um papers that we've relatively
extensively discussed
and so these are are not like the only
or the canonical papers or anything but
there's a lot of important ones in there
so
especially if you're interested in
looking at papers where like people in
the lab might have familiarity or
there's some things to listen to or
watch about it
then these are some good places to start
all right
awesome
next question
all right this is a contextualization
question
this is not a metadata contextualizing
sentence
on page 9 and 10 they talk about
differences from alternative frameworks
for example in contrast with other
frameworks
policy selection in active inference
automatically balances exploration and
exploitation
and later active inference extends the
inferential approach to domains of
cognition that are rarely considered
what are
five to seven examples
names in a sentence of other theories
and frameworks that active inference
improves upon or updates
anyone can raise their hand this is an
excellent um
homework
flash collaborative stigma g question
because even if each person only thought
of one novel
answer here
with a link and a name or somebody
improved what somebody else had already
brought
very quickly
as a textbook group we could have like
quite a coherent and comprehensive list
the idea of balancing exploration and
exploitation
so called is going to be
a key
theme
and the way that active inference
does
handle
this trade-off
not through the use of like an
exploratory mode or exploitative mode or
some parameter that is like governing
the the handoff there like some sort of
you know
x times exploration
plus one minus x of exploitation
that is like one approach that's
commonly used but
it would be
um a question of like where you know
which citations use that type of an
approach
and it's
going to come
to the epistemic and pragmatic value
whereas
um when there's little epistemic value
to be gleaned little informational
uncertainty result to resolve
then pragmatic value can be pursued
which is
reducing the surprise about
outcomes in relationship to preferences
and then on the other hand when there's
a lot of uncertainty
exploratory behavior might be engaged in
because there isn't enough
certainty around how to pursue those
pragmatic aims
and these are going to come into play
with like the team
mouse model that's going to be later in
the book
but this is a great question so anyone
want to like just give an example of
some other theory or framework
or some other approach to thinking about
exploration exploitation
one starting reading if anyone is
interested there is a 2015 paper
that is looking at exploration and
exploitation trade-offs
in different domains ali
well i don't know if it necessarily
improves upon but
certainly an alternative approach to
this theory
can be
stephen grossberg's art theory the
adaptive resonance theory that we talked
about a previous session
in that theory
uh the problem of learning and cognition
uh is attacked from the viewpoint of
solving
the stability slash plasticity dilemma
and uh in this context in the context of
art or adaptive resonance theory uh well
uh
or
let's say the difference between the
active imprint one of the main
differences between the active imprints
or any
predictive coding schemes
from
adaptive resonance theory is that
in bayesian models
generally
the fully
fully
suppressive matching
circuits uh i mean uh the uh
[Music]
the circuits that can propagate the
information it cannot solve the
stability slash plasticity dilemma as
opposed to the art or adaptive resonance
theory
so plasticity being more exploratory and
openness to updates
and stability being more like parametric
lock-in
more exploitative within a certain um
well yeah the plasticity refers to a
system that doesn't have
uh catastrophic
catastrophic forgetfulness
awesome
cool so we can just you know have this
question up and check back and people
can add things we'll just look at a few
more questions
so
on page 8 they write
the high road perspective is useful to
understand the normative nature of
active inference
what the living organisms must do to
face their fundamental existential
challenges
minimize free energy
and why the what and the why in the high
road
why to vicariously minimize the surprise
of their sensory observations
what does it mean to minimize surprise
vicariously
so someone has written
interesting choice of words here are two
possible answers also the authors or
the readers participants may have
something else in mind
vicarious might refer to the point on
page six that agents cannot tractably
minimize surprise as the authors
technically defined it
in chapter two coming up
so instead they're going to minimize an
approximation to surprise which is
variational free energy
however i'm not sure if they're
referring to
the two
types of surprise that are going to be
approached in chapter two which is the
marginal surprise
um like informational surprise and then
the bayesian surprise
or both
so one option is
surprise as defined
one way or the other or both
cannot be directly
calculated or it's not tractable to to
pursue and so the vicarious could mean
like indirect or via a proxy
and in that case something like
variational free energy is being
vicariously minimized and then that is
going to be used to
get at the surprise minimization and the
second option the person has written
vicarious might refer to the point that
agents minimize free energy not only in
response to real sensory observations
but in anticipation of them
those anticipations could come from
internal simulations by subroutines or
other modules or memory from recall of
past observed events
page 32 which is probably in chapter two
the authors seem to be referring to
engaging models vicariously in a counter
factual sense dealing with imagined
surprise at presumed observations
so these are really important comments
we have the indirect minimization of
surprise
using a proxy
so some type of heuristic to minimizing
surprise now
and so that is vicarious but
contemporary
and then the second sense
is
whether we're using a proxy or not
is referring to
um
[Music]
observations that haven't occurred so
anticipated or expected observations
some of these hopefully we'll come back
to in chapter two
but these are important questions and
it's gonna speak to
like variational free energy
and expected free energy and free energy
of the expected future a few other
constructs
stephen and yeah and then
yeah i put that last comment and i was
just thinking that should probably go
under number two there so i guess that
would be
evidence of that second interpretation
thank you
okay
so we'll maybe return to this in um
chapter two
okay let's just see if we can look up
just a few of these questions it's
awesome like how many there are and of
course anyone can always
read and contribute asynchronously
all right
the subtitle of the book is the free
energy principle in mind brain and
behavior what is the relevant
distinction
between mind and brain in the context of
the free energy principle
someone has written really appreciate
how the researchers have started
proposing biological implementations of
active in the brain
but it's not clear to me how this maps
onto related psychological concepts like
colloquial surprise predictions salience
arousal
yeah awesome and there's been some
recent work and some work that we're
going to be looking at in um
live stream 46
on active inference and folk psychology
about connecting some of the formalisms
to to folk psychological concepts so
that's one
place we'll be
looking at that but
um
[Music]
how does
or does active approach this mind brain
question
whether the cartesian
duelist question
hard problem of consciousness
intentional stance of dennit
why is the subtitle of the book that way
jessica and then anyone else with their
hand
um yes i mean i don't know to the answer
but
i
i guess make a guess i think maybe they
um mind will be more the cognition and
the brain looking at the physiology
and
and then you know looking at behaviors
that would be my guess
yeah awesome
bacterium does not have a brain
but does it have a mind
also
great questions we'll just continue just
these
questions with fewer upvotes because
there's such a bunch just so we can get
them in
so
generative model is used in the singular
or
is used in the singular as in the
generative model
or in the plural as in hierarchical
generative models
is a generative model composed of
generative models i.e is it structurally
fractal
someone has written personally i think
the answer is yes
or it's possible to answer yes
via referencing a paper that talks about
blankets of blankets markov blankets
life this paper definitely
does um think about the nesting of
multi-scale complex systems
in terms of like nested generative
models
that then
are
constituting
yes
that are then constituting um generative
models at a higher level
so like there's people with their
generative model and then the team has a
generative model of a different type jf
yes but even in individual
myself yourself
um
it can be could be characterized as
having a generative model
composed of uh
other general models dealing with uh
less abstract uh umvelt for example
so i i think i think yes i think almost
trivially in the sense of a collective
but in the sense of an individual uh
does an individual also
can be said to possess a generative
model that is itself composed of
sub-generative models
awesome point and we've
in several
live streams and settings discussed like
there's one sense where nesting is used
to refer to systems that are like
potentially even physically nested
and then we also see the nesting
architecture
for example here it's live stream number
when we discussed it but this is a
nesting
of
attentional and cognitive models
so this is even of a so-called
individual so what is it
about model nesting when sometimes it
can refer to
physical enclosure
and other times it is something that
enables counter factual reasoning
attention and metacognition
so what is the nesting and and if
someone is just seeing this kind of a
notation or this kind of a graph for the
first time we're gonna totally
go into it but it's gonna be one of the
core formalisms and also this paper is
going to deal with nested models and
other papers do the textbook is going to
spend almost all the time
um on just one level so just sort of the
kernel or the essence or the archetype
or the essential motif
of this partially observable markov
decision process
and the textbook is going to focus on
juxtaposing the discrete time
partially observable markov decision
process with a continuous time
but it will deal less with hierarchical
nesting but it does bring it up but it's
not going to be focused on
okay
what is the information content of a
prediction
i'm just going to read these ones just
so that those who are listening can see
like the kinds of questions that they
could be adding or addressing
this question has to do with the
relationship between active inference
and pleasant surprises
potentially even love languages
receiving money on the pavement
page five
is uh speaking to the author's rhetoric
around theory proliferation and
integration where basically they are
saying well we could have a dedicated
explanation for every neurotransmitter
for every synaptic junction every unique
behavior every cognitive phenomena
or we could somehow utilize first
principles whatever those are to result
in theory integration
and that gets mapped onto the scruffies
and the neats
is it really helpful to redefine terms
such as probability and surprise to
sometimes mean utility
and diversions from utility if that's
what the authors are doing there appears
to be an unhealthy ambiguity in how they
use these terms
this is where the formalisms are gonna
really come into play
um and also the um
[Music]
the live stream on
free energy a user's guide
deals with this um dual interpretation
of expectations and preferences and this
is like one of the most essential
differences between active inference and
reward learning or reinforcement
learning frameworks
is a dual
deployment of the same variable
in formalisms
to represent preferred states as well as
expected states
like homeostatic range is expected and
preferred it's where one wants to be
found and it's where one expects to be
found and so one can realize those
preferences by reducing their surprise
about the observations rather than
saying well homeostatic states are
valuable and we're going to pursue
maximum value
i might it be
how might an acceptable state space
relate to the idea of a comfort zone
it seems the acceptable state space for
an organism is necessary for it to
persist whereas a comfort zone seems to
be a less necessary state repertoire
which if exceeded may only indicate to
an organism that it's at risk of leaving
the acceptable state space
interesting
and then the last written question here
looking ahead into part two have people
been looking in the computational
complexity of the active inference model
and how far are we in terms of making
this computable
and the reference 2019 paper
computational resource demands of the
predictive bayesian brain
excellent and important
question to understand like the
analytical computational complexity like
the big o notation does nesting a model
make it two or is it you know log the
number of levels or is it number of
levels to the sum exponent
um and then also in practice like using
active block for ins or pi mdp
what is the actual runtime of different
algorithms
so
um
this is awesome with the questions that
everyone's added to one like we're going
to keep on returning to chapter one just
like we're going to keep on returning to
the ideas but people can fold it
and continue to add to two
and to the appendices which we're gonna
go to next week um so just as a reminder
next week we're going to be
approaching appendix a and b
which are mathematical
and so just a few thoughts on that
before we return back to the ideas in
the book
in appendix a
you can see that all the equations have
already been added
so if anyone like wants to reference
like what does equation a point 44 mean
um and obviously like there's 60
equations and you could get your
phd learning about some sub function of
just one so we're just trying to
familiarize and get a first coat of
paint so for those with different
mathematical backgrounds
if somebody can derive the proof
amazing
let's take some notes on it and if
somebody is just going to be asking
beginner questions that's also very
important so
that will be in next week's questions
and discussions
but let's just look at what ideas people
wrote and then see if there's any ideas
percolating
so
um
having addressed
some specific uncertainties i get with
the questions we can think about like
what are some impressions that people
were having
and like what was exciting ideas
so if um ben or mike want to
speak to this or if anybody else like
wants to share something jf and then
anyone else
yeah
jf then ben or is your hand raised
no my hand was not raised i'm sorry ben
go for it
yeah thanks can you hear me yep
cool uh yeah maybe i should have posed
this as a question actually i just
thought it was it was interesting this
connection between perception and
learning as essentially the same process
unfolding over different
time scales
because on the one hand this makes sense
to me because one example of learning
might be you can imagine an agent move
into a new city
with which they're completely unfamiliar
and the agent could
sit at a fixed point in the city or walk
around the city and just perceive the
city and they would learn over a longer
time scale they would observe certain
regularities or certain occurrences
and clearly that's one form of learning
but then there's maybe another example
where
you know my mathematical background's
fairly weak and so if i were to try and
learn the kind of fundamentals of the
equations that we were just looking at
um no matter how for how long i
kind of perceive those equations
i'm not going to learn them there's
going to be that i have no access to
kind there's no information gained there
it seems like to learn certain things we
need to scaffold perception
in certain ways and so i suppose my
question would be
when somebody teaches us something that
we don't understand is that merely a
kind of scaffolded perception
or is that kind of learning underwritten
by distinct cognitive processing
um completely separate from perception
great question thanks for unpacking that
and to give one
uh thought
let's imagine a ball moving across the
visual field
it seems like a canonical example of
perception we're perceiving the ball but
it could also be understood as parameter
updating or parameter learning
of
the location of the ball
and then
that's one approach but then also you
pointed towards like this deeper sense
of learning referring to like the
underlying structures like in the ball
movement examples it seems like learning
and perception
are the same but then learning might
also refer to something deeper like the
tendencies of how balls move or one
could
as probably many of us have look at
these
symbols
and perceive them visually
but because we wouldn't have learned the
underlying generative model
that gives rise to these pixels we could
continually be surprised
so what is happening when there's
perception and learning
seemingly happening hand in hand
and then other times where somebody's
speaking a language you don't understand
you certainly hear it you may even be
paying attention to it
yet the next phoneme may still
continually surprise you
so it's a really important question
and
then um mike wrote um
yes please go for it mike
yeah uh so
i think
these are straightforward but
foundational concepts that the
dependence of sensory input on action
and vice versa
creates a framework where we can have
feedback and then
the mathematical constructs let us think
about how we model that and simulate it
thanks for this
also essential point in active inference
there isn't a perception and inference
module that passes the perceptions to
the learning module and the learning
module passes it to the decision making
module the decision making modules of
the action model the inference is
conditioned upon policy selection and
action
and that is going to approach this nexus
of perception cognition and action
in an integrated way that not
that may differ from other frameworks
which was also to the point of that
um
previous question
so
this was um an awesome
session everyone really
appreciated it
i'll upload the video recording
bala following the meeting
next week at the same time we'll be
looking at questions and ideas from
appendix a and b
so just approach those however you'd
like and annotate the coda
and
uh also if anybody wants to like specify
another time when they just want to
discuss or co-work
that can be added
or
in the actin flap discord people can
like join it we can have like a voice
like a study hour or just a time to talk
about stuff or write down the questions
we have so
awesome work everybody thanks a lot